<!--The Official Report of Parliamentary Debates (Hansard) of the Legislative Council and the House of Assembly of the Parliament of South Australia are covered by parliamentary privilege. Republication by others is not afforded the same protection and may result in exposure to legal liability if the material is defamatory. You may copy and make use of excerpts of proceedings where (1) you attribute the Parliament as the source, (2) you assume the risk of liability if the manner of your use is defamatory, (3) you do not use the material for the purpose of advertising, satire or ridicule, or to misrepresent members of Parliament, and (4) your use of the extracts is fair, accurate and not misleading. Copyright in the Official Report of Parliamentary Debates is held by the Attorney-General of South Australia.-->
<hansard id="" tocId="" xml:lang="EN-AU" schemaVersion="1.0" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="hansard_1_0.xsd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2007/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <name>House of Assembly</name>
  <date date="2019-02-13" />
  <sessionName>Fifty-Fourth Parliament, First Session (54-1)</sessionName>
  <parliamentNum>54</parliamentNum>
  <sessionNum>1</sessionNum>
  <parliamentName>Parliament of South Australia</parliamentName>
  <house>House of Assembly</house>
  <venue></venue>
  <reviewStage>published</reviewStage>
  <startPage num="4543" />
  <endPage num="4648" />
  <dateModified time="2019-06-05T16:45:27+09:30" />
  <proceeding>
    <name>Matter of Privilege</name>
    <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000001">
      <heading>Matter of Privilege</heading>
    </text>
    <subject>
      <name>Matter of Privilege</name>
      <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000002">
        <heading>Matter of Privilege</heading>
      </text>
      <talker role="member" id="633" kind="speech">
        <name>The Hon. A. KOUTSANTONIS</name>
        <house>House of Assembly</house>
        <electorate id="">West Torrens</electorate>
        <startTime time="2019-02-13T13:59:59" />
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000003">
          <timeStamp time="2019-02-13T13:59:59" />
          <by role="member" id="633">The Hon. A. KOUTSANTONIS (West Torrens) (13:59):</by>  Sir, I rise on a matter of privilege. On 12 February the Leader of the Opposition asked the Premier the following question:</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000004">
          <inserted>Supplementary question to the Premier: given the Premier's previous answer, will the Premier rule out reversing the deal his minister agreed with the upstream states, as called for by the royal commissioner Bret Walker QC? With your leave, Mr Speaker, and that of the house I will explain.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text continued="true" id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000005">Leave was then granted, sir. The Leader of the Opposition went on to explain:</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000006">
          <inserted>The royal commissioner states, on pages 414 and 415 of his report, and I quote:</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000007">
          <inserted>'…no minister acting reasonably could consider these changes to the criteria to be anything but totally antipathetic to the interests of South Australia, and the South Australian environment. South Australia's agreement to these changes should be immediately reversed.'</inserted>
        </text>
        <text continued="true" id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000008">In response, the Premier told the House of Assembly:</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000009">
          <inserted>There was, sir, and most of it incorrect because—…</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000010">
          <inserted>If there's just some chance I might be able to answer the question, I can explain to those opposite. The Leader of the Opposition said, 'Will you rule out the recommendation of the royal commissioner?' This was not a recommendation of the royal commissioner…</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000011">
          <inserted>And now the guy who wants to be the leader thinks it was a finding. Look, the reality was—…</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000012">
          <inserted>I know those opposite, busy with those by-elections, had no chance to actually read a report that was so critical to our state, nor the Australian Productivity Commission report. We did. The reality is there are 111 findings…</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000013">
          <inserted>We have read it: 111 findings; none of them related to that issue…</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000014">
          <inserted>There were dozens of recommendations; none of them related to that issue. Read the report.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text continued="true" id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000015">His statement is incorrect and misleading. On page 62 of the royal commission report, in Key Findings, entitled Chapter 9: Efficiency Measures and the 450 GL, finding 9.10 states:</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000016">
          <inserted>The recent criteria agreed at the Murray-Darling Basin Ministerial Council meeting on 14 December 2018, at the behest of the Victorian and New South Wales governments, is another example of the lack of commitment by the commonwealth, New South Wales and Victoria to delivering the 450GL. The South Australian government's agreement to changes to the socio-economic criteria for efficiency measures is antipathetic to the interests of South Australia, and the South Australian environment. It is doubtful that much of the 450GL of upwater will ever be actually recovered for the environment through efficiency measures, and especially under the new criteria agreed.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text continued="true" id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000017">Further, the royal commission then, in Responses to Terms of Reference, Key Findings and Recommendations, on page 73 makes recommendation No. 11, and I quote:</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000018">
          <inserted>If efficiency measures are retained as a means of recovering water for the environment, including the 450GL, no changes should be made to the test for determining neutral or improved socio-economic outcomes in sec 7.17(2)(b) of the basin plan. Insofar as the criteria agreed at the Murray-Darling Basin Ministerial Council meeting on 14 December 2018 alter that test, they should be abandoned as they were likely to result in the failure to recover that water.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text continued="true" id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000019">I believe that the Premier has deliberately and intentionally—</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000020">
          <event kind="interjection">Members interjecting:</event>
        </text>
      </talker>
      <talker kind="speech" role="office">
        <name>The Speaker</name>
        <house>House of Assembly</house>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000021">
          <by role="office">The SPEAKER</by>:  Order!</text>
      </talker>
      <talker role="member" id="633" kind="speech" continued="true">
        <name>The Hon. A. KOUTSANTONIS</name>
        <house>House of Assembly</house>
        <page num="4569" />
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000022">
          <by role="member" id="633">The Hon. A. KOUTSANTONIS:</by>  —misled the House of Assembly and that a prima facie case exists for the establishment of a privileges committee. I ask you, therefore, to give consideration to my matter of privilege and rule if a motion to establish a privileges committee should be given precedence over other business in the House of Assembly.</text>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000023">
          <event kind="interjection">Members interjecting:</event>
        </text>
      </talker>
      <talker kind="speech" role="office">
        <name>The Speaker</name>
        <house>House of Assembly</house>
        <text id="2019021398180c57e54745e6b0000024">
          <by role="office">The SPEAKER:</by>  Order! Thank you, member for West Torrens. Obviously the Chair's role is confined to two aspects: (1) does the matter prima facie impinge on privilege and also deal with whether the matter is of such importance that precedent should be given to dealing with it as soon as possible. There is a fair bit in that, so I will defer my decision and come back to the house once we have processed it and asked for all relevant materials. I imagine most of them have been handed to me.</text>
      </talker>
    </subject>
  </proceeding>
</hansard>