<!--The Official Report of Parliamentary Debates (Hansard) of the Legislative Council and the House of Assembly of the Parliament of South Australia are covered by parliamentary privilege. Republication by others is not afforded the same protection and may result in exposure to legal liability if the material is defamatory. You may copy and make use of excerpts of proceedings where (1) you attribute the Parliament as the source, (2) you assume the risk of liability if the manner of your use is defamatory, (3) you do not use the material for the purpose of advertising, satire or ridicule, or to misrepresent members of Parliament, and (4) your use of the extracts is fair, accurate and not misleading. Copyright in the Official Report of Parliamentary Debates is held by the Attorney-General of South Australia.-->
<hansard id="" tocId="" xml:lang="EN-AU" schemaVersion="1.0" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="hansard_1_0.xsd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2007/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <name>Legislative Council</name>
  <date date="2019-02-27" />
  <sessionName>Fifty-Fourth Parliament, First Session (54-1)</sessionName>
  <parliamentNum>54</parliamentNum>
  <sessionNum>1</sessionNum>
  <parliamentName>Parliament of South Australia</parliamentName>
  <house>Legislative Council</house>
  <venue></venue>
  <reviewStage>published</reviewStage>
  <startPage num="2745" />
  <endPage num="2794" />
  <dateModified time="2019-02-28T14:57:26+10:30" />
  <proceeding continued="true">
    <name>Matters of Interest</name>
    <subject>
      <name>Cypriot Community</name>
      <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000001">
        <heading>Cypriot Community</heading>
      </text>
      <talker role="member" id="599" kind="speech">
        <name>The Hon. J.S.L. DAWKINS</name>
        <house>Legislative Council</house>
        <startTime time="2019-02-27T16:06:05" />
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000002">
          <timeStamp time="2019-02-27T16:06:05" />
          <by role="member" id="599">The Hon. J.S.L. DAWKINS (16:06):</by>  I rise to speak today about two recent Cyprus community events. On 9 February this year, I attended the 2019 Cyprus Festival in Welland. The festival was presented by the Cyprus Community South Australia as a two-day event celebrating the Cypriot way of life, past and present and in Australia. The Cyprus Community SA Incorporated was established in 1948, so there is a rich history of people from Cyprus as part of the everyday life of South Australia as we see it today.</text>
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000003">The festival celebrated the rich culture and entertainment that has come to our community from Cyprus. It was quite an experience, and the event is growing larger year by year. The event featured cultural demonstrations; dancing performances from individuals and Cypriot dancing groups, including adults and children in traditional costumes; live music; and plentiful delicious Cypriot food, including drinks and sweets. There were an estimated 2,000 attendees at the festival.</text>
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000004">I would particularly like to acknowledge and thank Professor Andreas Evdokiou, who is the president of the Cyprus Community of South Australia; Mr Loukas Minas, the secretary of the Cyprus Community of South Australia; and Ms Christina Loucas, who is the Cyprus Community SA coordinator.</text>
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000005">I know that the City of Charles Sturt is a great supporter of the event and goes to some effort to assist in the management of traffic and other things in relation to the festival. I was pleased to see Mayor Angela Evans at the event, paying tribute to the volunteers, mainly from the Cypriot community but I think also other individuals who did work behind the scenes to make the festival such an enjoyable and successful event.</text>
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000006">I acknowledge the presence at the event (when I was there) of Mr Matt Cowdrey, the member for Colton in the other place, who was representing the Premier; the Hon. Connie Bonaros; the Hon. Frank Pangallo; the Hon. Irene Pnevmatikos; as well as the member for West Torrens in the other place. I look forward to making another visit to the festival, as it has become one that I look forward to on a regular basis.</text>
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000007">On 18 February, I attended the 2019 Adelaide Cobras season launch in Hilton. The Adelaide Cobras Football Club was founded by the Cypriot community in 1972 and is affiliated with the Football Federation South Australia National League structure. The season launch was held at the Hilton Hotel and I was pleased that the Hon. Russell Wortley was also able to attend the event.</text>
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000008">Originally, the club was known as Adelaide Omonia to signify unity with Adelaide and its surrounding communities and suburbs. The name was changed to Adelaide Cobras in 1994. The event included an introduction of senior teams, the announcement of club captains and the acknowledgment of valuable sponsors. I would particularly like to acknowledge the leadership of the Adelaide Cobras Football Club, including Mr Simon Panayi, president; Mr Paul Soteriou, vice-president; Mr Peter Gonis, secretary; and Mr Con Nicola, treasurer.</text>
        <page num="2769" />
        <text id="20190227062d23a0ff8f419da0000009">Many of us in this place recognise that the support that we and the general community give to local sporting teams is vital and valuable, and certainly the opportunities I have to support local sporting events and groups that not only represent particular facets of the community but provide a way in which many people learn about leadership, and a way in which they can develop themselves as part of our broader community. I wish the Adelaide Cobras Football Club all the best for the 2019 season and success in the near future.</text>
      </talker>
    </subject>
  </proceeding>
</hansard>