<hansard id="" tocId="" xml:lang="EN-AU" schemaVersion="1.0" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="hansard_1_0.xsd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2007/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <name>Legislative Council</name>
  <date date="2019-02-12" />
  <sessionName>Fifty-Fourth Parliament, First Session (54-1)</sessionName>
  <parliamentNum>54</parliamentNum>
  <sessionNum>1</sessionNum>
  <parliamentName>Parliament of South Australia</parliamentName>
  <house>Legislative Council</house>
  <venue></venue>
  <reviewStage>published</reviewStage>
  <startPage num="2527" />
  <endPage num="2572" />
  <dateModified time="2019-02-25T11:19:35+10:30" />
  <proceeding continued="true">
    <name>Answers to Questions</name>
    <subject>
      <name>Coal Gasification</name>
      <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000001">
        <inserted>
          <heading>Coal Gasification</heading>
        </inserted>
      </text>
      <talker role="member" id="3130" kind="question">
        <name>The Hon. M.C. PARNELL</name>
        <house>Legislative Council</house>
        <questions>
          <question date="2019-02-12">
            <name>Coal Gasification</name>
          </question>
        </questions>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000002">
          <inserted>In reply to <by role="member" id="3130">the Hon. M.C. PARNELL </by>(13 November 2018).  </inserted>
        </text>
      </talker>
      <talker role="member" id="1820" kind="answer">
        <name>The Hon. D.W. RIDGWAY</name>
        <house>Legislative Council</house>
        <portfolios>
          <portfolio id="">
            <name>Minister for Trade</name>
          </portfolio>
        </portfolios>
        <questions>
          <question date="2019-02-12">
            <name>Coal Gasification</name>
          </question>
        </questions>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000003">
          <inserted>
            <by role="member" id="1820">The Hon. D.W. RIDGWAY (Minister for Trade, Tourism and Investment):</by>  The Minister for Mining and Energy has advised</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000004">
          <inserted>1.&amp;#x9;The independent experts used in the state government's assessment of the Leigh Creek Energy demonstration project for underground coal gasification, or UCG, include:</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000005">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Ikon Science, technical consultants in the field of geomechanical modelling.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000006">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories, renowned international experts in UCG based in the United States.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000007">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Dr Gary J. Love, fact witness to the Queensland Department of Environment and Science in the investigation and prosecution of Linc Energy.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000008">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Dr Clifford Mallett, former CSIRO UCG research scientist.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000009">
          <inserted>The independent experts were selected based on their expertise in their respective fields and for being at arms-length to the Leigh Creek Energy demonstration project. </inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000010">
          <inserted>The advice provided by the independent experts is publicly available on the Department for Energy and Mining website.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000011">
          <inserted>2.&amp;#x9;The state government did not engage Professor Campbell Gemmell as an independent expert. However, findings from Professor Gemmell's independent review of UCG commissioned by the Scottish government, were considered in the state government's assessment of the Leigh Creek Energy demonstration project. In his review, Professor Gemmel concludes that establishing credible baselines, firm planning and licensing conditions and subsequently enforcing robust regulatory, monitoring and liability management arrangements would be paramount to the realisation of any successful UCG project. It is exactly for these reasons that in South Australia through the Petroleum and Geothermal Energy Act 2000, licensees are required to undertake sufficient exploration, appraisal and site assessments to enable informed evidence- and fact-based regulatory decisions on any UCG proposal in this state. Further details are provided in the assessment summary report for the Leigh Creek Energy demonstration project, available on the Department for Energy and Mining website.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000012">
          <inserted>Website link:</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="20190212131802292dde4cd7a0000013">
          <item sublevel="2">
            <inserted>http://energymining.sa.gov.au/petroleum/projects/prj_leigh_creek_energy_isg.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
      </talker>
    </subject>
  </proceeding>
</hansard>