<hansard id="" tocId="" xml:lang="EN-AU" schemaVersion="1.0" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="hansard_1_0.xsd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2007/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <name>House of Assembly</name>
  <date date="2019-02-14" />
  <sessionName>Fifty-Fourth Parliament, First Session (54-1)</sessionName>
  <parliamentNum>54</parliamentNum>
  <sessionNum>1</sessionNum>
  <parliamentName>Parliament of South Australia</parliamentName>
  <house>House of Assembly</house>
  <venue></venue>
  <reviewStage>published</reviewStage>
  <startPage num="4649" />
  <endPage num="4730" />
  <dateModified time="2019-06-05T16:55:08+09:30" />
  <proceeding continued="true">
    <name>Answers to Questions</name>
    <subject>
      <name>Auditor-General's Report</name>
      <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000001">
        <inserted>
          <heading>Auditor-General's Report</heading>
        </inserted>
      </text>
      <talker role="member" id="4842" kind="question">
        <name>The Hon. S.C. MULLIGHAN</name>
        <house>House of Assembly</house>
        <electorate id="">Lee</electorate>
        <questions>
          <question date="2019-02-14">
            <name>Auditor-General's Report</name>
          </question>
        </questions>
        <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000002">
          <inserted>In reply to <by role="member" id="4842">the Hon. S.C. MULLIGHAN (Lee)</by> (28 November 2018).  </inserted>
        </text>
      </talker>
      <talker role="member" id="4338" kind="answer">
        <name>The Hon. S.S. MARSHALL</name>
        <house>House of Assembly</house>
        <electorate id="">Dunstan</electorate>
        <portfolios>
          <portfolio id="">
            <name>Premier</name>
          </portfolio>
        </portfolios>
        <questions>
          <question date="2019-02-14">
            <name>Auditor-General's Report</name>
          </question>
        </questions>
        <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000003">
          <inserted>
            <by role="member" id="4338">The Hon. S.S. MARSHALL (Dunstan—Premier):</by>  I have been advised:</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000004">
          <inserted>Renewal SA provides a regular written and verbal report to myself on potential tenancies under commercial negotiation, as well as the confirmed tenancy schedule at Lot Fourteen, as provided to them by their commercial leasing agent Colliers International. This same information is provided to the Office of the Chief Entrepreneur.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000005">
          <inserted>There are currently six committed tenants at Lot Fourteen—Chamonix IT Consulting, Myriota, Daitum, Core Energy and Resources, the Office of the SA Chief Entrepreneur and the Australian Institute of Machine Learning (noting that the Australian Institute of Machine Learning has executed an Agreement for Lease and will move into Lot Fourteen on completion of refurbishment works to the Women's Health Centre). Additional tenants confirmed to move in during 2019 are – FIXE@Lot Fourteen Start-up Hub, Defence Landing Pad and the Australian Space Agency.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000006">
          <inserted>Renewal SA also provides an updated tenancy schedule and pipeline of tenant leads on a regular basis. This reporting includes number of leads, available area under negotiation, spatial requirement per tenant and number of employees, lease term, anticipated lease commencement and status of negotiation.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902147b31e3457db945d790000007">
          <inserted>The specific details of tenant lease arrangements are commercial in confidence, but I can advise that the rents paid by tenants are benchmarked and equivalent with commercial rental rates in the Adelaide CBD for similar building classifications. There are no tenants or occupants currently at Lot Fourteen on rent-free deals.</inserted>
        </text>
      </talker>
    </subject>
  </proceeding>
</hansard>