<!--The Official Report of Parliamentary Debates (Hansard) of the Legislative Council and the House of Assembly of the Parliament of South Australia are covered by parliamentary privilege. Republication by others is not afforded the same protection and may result in exposure to legal liability if the material is defamatory. You may copy and make use of excerpts of proceedings where (1) you attribute the Parliament as the source, (2) you assume the risk of liability if the manner of your use is defamatory, (3) you do not use the material for the purpose of advertising, satire or ridicule, or to misrepresent members of Parliament, and (4) your use of the extracts is fair, accurate and not misleading. Copyright in the Official Report of Parliamentary Debates is held by the Attorney-General of South Australia.-->
<hansard id="" tocId="" xml:lang="EN-AU" schemaVersion="1.0" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="hansard_1_0.xsd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2007/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <name>Legislative Council</name>
  <date date="2019-02-12" />
  <sessionName>Fifty-Fourth Parliament, First Session (54-1)</sessionName>
  <parliamentNum>54</parliamentNum>
  <sessionNum>1</sessionNum>
  <parliamentName>Parliament of South Australia</parliamentName>
  <house>Legislative Council</house>
  <venue></venue>
  <reviewStage>published</reviewStage>
  <startPage num="2527" />
  <endPage num="2572" />
  <dateModified time="2019-02-25T11:19:35+10:30" />
  <proceeding continued="true">
    <name>Answers to Questions</name>
    <subject>
      <name>Torrens to Torrens Project</name>
      <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000001">
        <inserted>
          <heading>Torrens to Torrens Project</heading>
        </inserted>
      </text>
      <talker role="member" id="3404" kind="question">
        <name>The Hon. J.A. DARLEY</name>
        <house>Legislative Council</house>
        <questions>
          <question date="2019-02-12">
            <name>Torrens to Torrens Project</name>
          </question>
        </questions>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000002">
          <inserted>In reply to <by role="member" id="3404">the Hon. J.A. DARLEY </by>(18 October 2018).  </inserted>
        </text>
      </talker>
      <talker role="member" id="1820" kind="answer">
        <name>The Hon. D.W. RIDGWAY</name>
        <house>Legislative Council</house>
        <portfolios>
          <portfolio id="">
            <name>Minister for Trade</name>
          </portfolio>
        </portfolios>
        <questions>
          <question date="2019-02-12">
            <name>Torrens to Torrens Project</name>
          </question>
        </questions>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000003">
          <inserted>
            <by role="member" id="1820">The Hon. D.W. RIDGWAY (Minister for Trade, Tourism and Investment):</by>  The Minister for Transport, Infrastructure and Local Government has provided the following advice: </inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000004">
          <inserted>1.&amp;#x9;I am advised no formal records have been kept on the number of business that have closed, rather than relocated.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000005">
          <inserted>2.&amp;#x9;No, there has not been follow up. However, based upon lessons learned, when a project is announced, the Department of Planning, Transport and Infrastructure (DPTI) (or its contractors) will actively engage with businesses and business owners to obtain information specific to the business and form relationships and primary points of contact. Funding for marketing, advertising and communications campaigns will be embedded into the procurement process for major capital projects.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000006">
          <inserted>A $150,000 Bring Back Business also known as 'Love Local' campaign was approved by DPTI in November 2017 for the Torrens to Torrens (T2T) Alliance to work collaboratively with all of the affected businesses and offered ongoing support including: </inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000007">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Customer access flyers</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000008">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Directional signage</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000009">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Website links on the 'support local business' page</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000010">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Intranet promotion of 'meal deals' for workforces </inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000011">
          <inserted>Where appropriate, an independent small business advisor may be provided to assist business owners to continue to trade during construction with as little disruption as possible and provide business continuity strategies.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000012">
          <inserted>The Marshall government has released the small business engagement policy, designed to change the way it engages with the business community, to better protect businesses and minimise disruption during large infrastructure projects.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000013">
          <inserted>Since the announcement of the policy there has been a renewed focus on supporting local businesses on existing infrastructure projects.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000014">
          <inserted>3.&amp;#x9;Yes. I am advised the T2T Alliance provided the following assistance to assist Queen Street traders:</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000015">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Partnered with the Adelaide Business Hub at the start of the project. A letter was sent to all businesses within the project footprint, offering access to a tailored business support package (for small businesses with up to 20 staff) during construction, which included two hours free consultation and low cost assistance for marketing and business advice, training and development and promotional assistance.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000016">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Provided permanent signage on Port Road and South Road advising motorists how to access the Queen Street precinct. </inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000017">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Provided electronic and/or static signage when detours were in place on Port Road.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <page num="2568" />
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000018">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Provided $20,000 to fund a social media campaign for Queen Street traders.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000019">
          <item sublevel="1" bullet="true">
            <inserted>Provided opportunities for Queen Street traders to promote their businesses during works.</inserted>
          </item>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000020">
          <inserted>In addition to the above, construction activities impacting Queen Street traders were undertaken at night, where possible, to minimise disruption to businesses. </inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000021">
          <inserted>4.&amp;#x9;I am advised by the T2T Alliance that its records show 32 businesses contacted DPTI to discuss impacts on their business.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000022">
          <inserted>5. &amp; 6.&amp;#x9;The Marshall government has introduced formal guidelines for specific engagement with small businesses impacted by major capital works. As announced last month, these guidelines cement a firm commitment to work with businesses as early as possible in the process and provide greater transparency.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000023">
          <inserted>When a project is announced, DPTI (or its contractors) will actively engage with businesses and business owners to obtain information specific to the business, form relationships and obtain primary points of contact.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000024">
          <inserted>Funding for marketing, advertising and communications campaigns will be embedded into the procurement process for major capital projects. </inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000025">
          <inserted>Where appropriate, an independent small business advisor may be provided to assist business owners to continue to trade during construction with as little disruption as possible and suggest strategies for business owners.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000026">
          <inserted>This information and direct links to further resources for small business is available for businesses and the public on www.infrastructure.sa.gov.au.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000027">
          <inserted>DPTI and its contractors are committed to being transparent early in the engagement process and working with local businesses to lessen impacts of construction and work together as much as possible.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000028">
          <inserted>These measures are intended to maintain the flow of customers during construction and also attract customers back to an area once construction is finished.</inserted>
        </text>
        <text id="201902122ff2d28faded44c690000029">
          <inserted>Since the announcement of the policy there has been a renewed focus on supporting local businesses on existing infrastructure projects.</inserted>
        </text>
      </talker>
    </subject>
  </proceeding>
</hansard>